Maine Acadian Cultural Survey Collection
American Folklife Center, Library of Congress
- Series 3: Graphic materials, The original materials are stored at Ft. Meade.
  - Black-and-white negatives, 3130 35mm black-white-film negatives
    - Home of Camille DeVost, woodworker, Lille, Maine, July 03, 1991, AFC 1991/029: DW-B028-61407; David A. Whitman; 35 35 mm black-and-white film negatives
      These images document a visit to the home of Camille DeVost in Lille, ME. Mr. DeVost is a neighbor of Don Cyr; he is a woodworker who uses a tool called a crooked knife, which is a small draw knife, to carve ax handles; 2-14, Mr. DeVost demonstrated the making of an ax handle to field coordinator Ray Brassieur. Initial cutting is done with an axe (#2-7), and the handle is finished with a crooked knife (#8-14); 15-17, Mr. DeVost keeps his stock of finished handles hanging in his basement; 18-21, Don Cyr watches as DeVost shows how a handle is split to insert the head of the ax; 22-23, DeVost shows Brassieur some of his tools; 24, One of DeVost's crooked knives; 25-27, DeVost demonstrates the use of a crooked knife to Cyr and Brassieur; 28-30, Crooked knives and other tools at DeVost's basement workbench; 31, Ax handles hanging in the basement; 32-33, Brassieur and DeVost; 34-35, Handmade snowshoes hanging on the wall in DeVost's basement; snowshoe making was once an important craft in the area.
    - Various scenes, Upper St. John River area, Maine, July 03, 1991 - July 05, 1991, AFC 1991/029: DW-B029-61419; David A. Whitman; 36 35 mm black-and-white film negatives
      These images document a variety of scenes; 2-13, Site of former twin barn in Hamlin, ME; the barn was destroyed in a fire just a few days before; 14-16, Main St., downtown Fort Kent, ME; the buildings in downtown Fort Kent sprouted flags for July 4th weekend; 17-19, Patriotic message on downtown gas station, Fort Kent; 21-24, Farmland and farmstead in eastern Fort Kent; 25-29, Abandoned farm equipment, Fort Kent; the number of people in the study area who earn their livelihood from agriculture has steadily declined over the past thirty years; 30-33, Lots of visitors from out-of-state, particularl Connecticut, came to the area on July 4 th weekend. Connecticut has seen a large influx of migrants from northern Maine, a process which began in the Depression of the 1930s. This photograph was taken at Rosette's, a restaurant in Frenchville, ME, where an informal count showed nearly half the cars to have out-of-state license plates; 34-36, Tractor in potato field, Frenchville; 36a, Cars parked in Lavertu Settlement for the Lavertu family reunion; again, lots of Connecticut plates in evidence.
    - Lavertu family reunion, Lavertu Settlement, Maine, July 05, 1991, AFC 1991/029: DW-B030-61424; David A. Whitman; 36 35 mm black-and-white film negatives
      These images document a reunion of the Lavertu family held on Edgar Lavertu's farm in Lavertu Settlement, ME. The reunion drew family members from as far away as Florida, as well as many people from closer states like Massachusetts and Connecticut. A whole pig was barbecued for the reunion meal, and there were displays of memorabilia and souvenirs and a family history book compiled by Roger Lavertu offered for sale. A monument to the first Lavertu settlers of the area was unveiled and Roger Lavertu gave a brief oral family history; 1-11, Cars with a variety of out-of-state license plates; 12, Sign on one of Lavertu's barns; 13-21, More out-of-state cars; 22, Large quonset hut barn served as the location for the barbecue, souvenir and memorabilia displays, and entertainment; 23-24, One of the family members served as emcee (name unknown); 25-26, Wooden potato barrels in the barn; 27-28, Old family pictures; 29, Family members socialize in the doorway to the barn; 30, A couple of the youngsters provided some music on keyboard and drums; 31-33, Kids get a wagon ride; 34, Volleyball was a popular activity; 35-36, The crew in charge of the pig roast. The pig was purchased through Jess' Market in Frenchville; preparing pigs for roasts is one of Jess' specialties. Gerald Ouellette (white hat, mustache) of St. David, ME, was said to be the expert pig roaster.
    - Lavertu family reunion, Lavertu Settlement, Maine, July 05, 1991, AFC 1991/029: DW-B031-61410; David A. Whitman; 37 35 mm black-and-white film negatives
      These images document the reunion of the Lavertu family. See MAPDW-B030 for more information; 1, Inadvertent photo; 2, Some of the older family members are taken by wagon to the site of the memorial for the unveiling ceremony; 3, Everyone heads for the memorial; 4-20, Memorial unveiling ceremony; Roger Lavertu presented a short oral family history just prior to the actual unveiling (#10) and some young family musicians played a trumpet duet version of "The Star Spangled Banner" (#14-15); 21, The memorial, with names of many early settlers of the area; 22-30, Some of the older family members pose for photos at the memorial; 31-end, The pig is roasted in a cooker made from a fuel tank.
    - July 4th weekend celebration sponsored by Eagle Lake Parish, Eagle Lake, Maine; Meeting of American Folklife Center Maine Acadian Survey team, Lille, Eagle Lake, Maine, July 07, 1991 - July 08, 1991, AFC 1991/029: DW-B032-61411; David A. Whitman; 36 35 mm black-and-white film negatives
      These images document a two-day festival held in Eagle Lake, ME. The event was a benefit for the Eagle Lake Parish; 2-3, Large tents were set up to house food service, souvenir sales, and raffles; 4, Game tables; 5-6, Tents housing various festival activities; 7-8, Field coordinator Ray Brassieur buys some souvenirs; 10, Souvenir sales tent; 11-13, This family recipe cookbook was available for purchase; 14, Ticket sales for Sunday evening barbecue; 15, Brassieur's a sucker for memorabilia; 16-18, Raffle and souvenir sales tent; 19, Various home-made food was available; 21-23, Snack/sandwich tent; 24-25, Brassieur meets Beth Albert, who operated a small concession stand selling fried dough and chicken stew; 26, Looking over the selection of baked goods; 27-28, Beth Albert's concession stand; These images document an evening meeting at the Eagle Lake camp occupied by fieldworkers Ray Brassieur and David Whitman. The meeting was a planning and review session attended by fieldworkers Brassieur, Whitman, and Lisa Ornstein, and American Folklife Center staff members Alan Jabbour (Director), David Taylor (folklife specialist and Maine Acadian Project Supervisor), and Camilla Bryce-LaPorte (research specialist); 29, Left to right: Brassieur, Jabbour, Taylor, Ornstein; 30, left to right: Brassieur, Bryce-LaPorte, Taylor, Ornstein; 31, Bryce-LaPorte and Jabbour draw dishwashing detail; 32-end, Project team members discuss various aspects of the research and report.
    - Various buildings and scenes, Upper St. John River Valley area, Maine, July 09, 1991, AFC 1991/029: DW-B033-4032; David A. Whitman; 27 35 mm black-and-white film negatives
      These images document a variety of buildings and scenes; 1, Rectangular clothesline; this is a common type in the area; 2-3, House of decorative butterfly maker, State Highway 11, Wallagrass, ME. These decorative butterflies were displayed on the exterior of many houses in the study area; most appear to be made from scrap wood and handpainted a variety of colors; 4-5, Magic Shears Salon in Wallagrass; many residents have opened businesses in their houses, and beauty salons are one of the most often seen types; 6, Logging truck at a house in Wallagrass; independent trucking seems to be an important economic activity in the area; 7, Wooden "running potato" lawn decoration; potatoes are the primary crop in the study area, and these lawn decorations are fairly common; 8-9, Rectangular clothesline; 10-11, Forest and farmland, Wallagrass; a great deal of land in the area has gone out of agricultural production and is returning to forest; 13-15, Abandoned and decaying house in an area called the "back settlements." This house is of twentieth century construction judging by the materials, but it had birch bark insulation; 16-20, Wheeled dock called a quay on the western side of Eagle Lake. The wheels enable the dock to be removed from the water before the winter freeze, thus averting ice damage. Such docks are found on every lake in the study area; this one is longer than most, and has four wheels instead of the usual two. It seems to be in need of repair; 21-23, Another quay near Eagle Lake; the fenders are a most unusual feature; 24-25, Home and studio of Fort Kent sculptor and painter George Roy; the small statue of a logger near the door was made by Roy using a chainsaw; 26-27, The Forever Young Club, Madawaska, ME; a group of senior citizens holds a Saturday night dance here.
    - Various scenes, Upper St. John River area, Maine, July 10, 1991, AFC 1991/029: DW-B034-4045; David A. Whitman; 36 35 mm black-and-white film negatives
      These images document a variety of scenes; 2, Set-back mailbox with reflector, strategies to mark the box's location when the deep winter snows pile up, and try to avoid snowplow damage; 3-4, Mobile home with added gambrel roof. This roof style is popular on a variety of buildings in the study area, sometimes for functional but often for purely decorative reasons; 5-7, Decorative eagles on a house in Fort Kent; these are found throughout the study area; 8-14, Wheeled dock, locally called a quay. on Eagle Lake, ME; the wheels enable the dock to be removed from the water before the winter freeze, thus averting ice damage. The small motor boat is a type of craft often used on area lakes; These images document a visit to the home of Jerry and Jean White in Frenchville, ME, to see a wooden strip canoe being built by Jerry and Mark Jalbert of St. Agatha, ME. Canoes are common in the study area, but most are mass-produced fiberglass or ABS types; 15-30, Various views of the canoe under construction; 31-end, Jalbert (cap) and White work on the canoe.
    - Strip canoe. Frenchville, Maine; Various scenes, Frenchville, Maine, July 11, 1991, AFC 1991/029: DW-B035-4030; David A. Whitman; 36 35 mm black-and-white film negatives
      These images document the building of a strip canoe at the home of Jerry and Jean White in Frenchville, ME. See MAP-DW-B034 for more information; 2-6, Close-ups of canoe's construction; 7-10, Field coordinator Ray Brassieur talks with Mark Jalbert about the canoe; 11-14, Close-ups of the bow of the canoe; 15-18, The Whites' cat Amos does some field research in the trunk of Brassieur's car; 19-20, A neighbor of the Whites works his fields on a tractor; 21-22, These buildings were once large storage facilities called potato, houses; they are generally found by railroad tracks, as their function was to store the produce prior to shipping by rail. Most, although not all, of them are no longer used for their original purpose. Some stand empty; this one, on Market St. in Fort Kent, has been converted to commercial/retail space; 23-24, Monique's Hair Salon, Fort Kent; area residents often operate small business endeavors from their homes; salons are quite common in this arrangement; 25-27, Shrine in a yard in Fort Kent; such shrines are a common sight in the study area; 28-30, Eagles used as house decorations are seen throughout the area; 31-32, Mailboxes are often set back from the road to avoid being buried by snow or damaged by snowplows; 33-36, Rectangular clothesline, a common type in the area; 37, One of the more decorative approaches to mailbox support.
    - Various buildings and scenes, Fort Kent, Maine, July 12, 1991, AFC 1991/029: DW-B036-4047; David A. Whitman; 35 35 mm black-and-white film negatives
      These images document a variety of scenes in Fort Kent, ME; 2-3, Mailboxes are often set back from the road to help avoid snow and snowplow damage; 4-6, Potato grower Alberie Pelletier on his tractor, spraying one of his potato fields. Mr. Pelletier, like many growers, has several non-contiguous areas which he farms; 7-10, Farmland in eastern part of Fort Kent; 12, Sign on a telephone pole in Fort Kent; 13, Small herds of livestock are occasionally found on area farms; 14-17, More mailboxes; 18-21, Rectangular clothesline, a common type in the area; 22-25, Houses with lateral additions, State Highway 11, Fort Kent; this is one of the most common addition types in the study area. The broken rooflines and incised porches of these houses, while often associated with French architecture in North America, are not usually found on houses in this area; 26-31, Replica of Eiffel Tower in a yard in Fort Kent; 32-33, House with lateral addition; 34-35, Small shed with gambrel (colm-casse) roof; this roof style is found on a side variety of buildings throughout the study area; 36A, farmstead along Highway 11.
    - Various buildings and scenes, Wallagrass, Maine, July 13, 1991, AFC 1991/029: DW-B037-4027; David A. Whitman; 36 35 mm black-and-white film negatives
      These images document a variety of buildings and scenes in Wallagrass, ME; 2-3, Magic Shears Beauty Salon; area residents often operate business out of their homes, and salons are perhaps the most frequently found type; 4-5, Wheeled dock, locally called a quay. near Eagle Lake. Such docks are found throughout the study area; the wheels enable them to be pulled from the water before the winter freeze, thus averting ice damage; 6-7, Another quay, in Eagle Lake; 8-9, Butterflies, most of which seem to be hand-made and painted, are a common decorative feature on houses; 10-11, I & R Garage, Inc., Wallagrass; another example of business/residence combination; 12, A birdhouse made in the shape of the Fort Kent Blockhouse; 13-14, House with lateral addition, a style frequently found in the study area; 15-16, Decorative eagles are found on houses throughout the area; 17-18, Abandoned barn with collapsing roof; as agriculture declines in importance, more farm buildings are being abandoned. Some simply stand and decay, but a great many are torn down; 19-22, More decorative butterflies; 23-24, Decorative eagle; 25-26, Saucier's Store, State Highway 11, Wallagrass; small convenience/grocery stores are a frequently seen residence/business combination; 27-28, Mailbox set back from the road; this helps avoid damage by snow and snowplow; 29-30, Rectangularly-shaped clotheslines are a common type; 31-36, Abandoned farm buildings, including an old windmill (#33- 34), Highway 11, Wallagrass.
    - Various buildings and scenes, Fort Kent, Maine, July 10, 1991, AFC 1991/029: DW-B038-4023; David A. Whitman; 36 35 mm black-and-white film negatives
      These images document a variety of buildings and scenes in Fort Kent, ME; 2-3, Knights of Columbus hall; 4-7, Shed with gambrel roof, locally called colm-casse; this roof style is seen on a wide variety of buildings throughout the study area; 8-12, An assortment of gambrel-roofed buildings; 13-17, A house with decorative eagles; the wrought-iron eagle next to the top of the door is a type seen on a large number of houses and other buildings; the stenciled eagle on the door is an unusual style; 18, Semi-trailer with Ten Commandments painted on the side; 19-20, Another decorative wrought-iron eagle; 21-22, Mailbox set back from road to avoid damage from snow and snowplow; 23-25, Wrought iron eagle on a carport; 26-27, Hay fields in New Brunswick as seen from just south of U.S. Highway 1 in eastern Fort Kent; 28-29, House with a small section of gambrel roof; here, as in #8-10 above, the effect is decorative rather than functional; 30-33, A small structure of the type often located behind or next to houses and used for firewood storage; 34-35, Firewood storage structure; 36, Wildflowers along the road (wildflowers?? in black and white?? oops.); 37, Set back mailbox.
    - Dance at Forever Young Club, Madawaska, Maine, July 13, 1991, AFC 1991/029: DW-B039-4043; David A. Whitman; 36 35 mm black-and-white film negatives
      These images document a Saturday night dance at the Forever Young Club in Madawaska, ME. This dance is apparently part of a circuit of such dances held at various locations in the upper St. John river valley, in both the Maine and New Brunswick. The music for this dance was provided by a father/son team, ??????? (fiddle and guitar); there was also synthesized percussion. The most popular dance was a mixer called "Lady of the Lake," which was danced several times during the evening to a variety of reel/hornpipe tunes. Some of the dances, including the "Lady of the Lake," were called; there were also couples dances that were not called. There were tables set up on both sides of the dance floor, and people would sit at these tables and socialize between dances; 2-14, A series of photographs taken during one of the early dances; 15-16, Field coordinator Ray Brassieur talks with the musicians; 17, Crucifix with rameau (blessed palm) and "Liquer forbidden" sign behind bandstand; 18-19, Folks socialize between dances; 20-21, The musicians; Cyrice Therrien, violin, Maurice Therrien, guitar; 22-end, Another dance; I believe this is a "Lady of the Lake."
    - Dance at Forever Young Club, Madawaska, Maine, July 13, 1991, AFC 1991/029: DW-B040-4035; David A. Whitman; 36 35 mm black-and-white film negatives
      These images document a dance at the Forever Young Club in Madawaska, ME. See MAP-DW-B039 for more information; 1-2, Dancers; 3-4, Club president Gerard Lagasse checks up on the band; 5-6, Left to right: fiddler Cyrice Therrien, guitarist Maurice Therrien (son of Cyrice), caller Reno Guerette; 7-end, A series of photographs taken during the course of a single dance.
    - Dance at Forever Young Club, Madawaska, Maine, July 13, 1991, AFC 1991/029: DW-B041-4033; David A. Whitman; 36 35 mm black-and-white film negatives
      These images document a dance at the Forever Young Club in Madawaska, ME. See MAP-DW-B039 for more information; 1-10, Dancers; 11-15, Musicians Cyrice Therrien, fiddle, and Maurice Therrien, guitar, with caller Reno Guerrette; 16-22, A dance which had a good deal of line dancing in it; 23, ??? Sirois talks to field coordinator Ray Brassieur (hidden behind wall); 24-26, Crucifix with rameau (blessed palm) on wall behind bandstand; 27-30, Sirois gives Brassieur hints on befriending the women at the dance; 31-32, Club president Gerard Lagasse makes some announcements; 33, Musicians and caller; 34, Dancers; 35, Some dance, some watch and talk; 36-36a, Dancers; notice that in this photo, as in several others, women often dance together as a couple.
    - Various scenes, Upper St. John River area, Maine, July 14, 1991, AFC 1991/029: DW-B042-4028; David A. Whitman; 36 35 mm black-and-white film negatives
      These images document a variety of scenes; 1, Inadvertent photo of chairs in Eagle Lake camp; 2-3, Twin barn on State Highway 161 in southeastern Fort Kent, ME; a number of such barns exist in the study area, most in better condition than this one; 4-5, Harvesting new potatoes along Highway 161 near Guerette, ME; we stopped when we saw a sign which advertised new potatoes for sale; 6-7, Sign advertising produce for sale; 8, Self service live bait; what a concept!!; These images document an event called Tintamarre, a kind of noisemaking competition held as part of the annual Grande Riviere Festival in Van Buren, ME, and St-Leonard, New Brunswick; 9-20, People gather in parking lots and on street corners in Van Buren, ME, before assembling to march to the international bridge between Van Buren and St-Leonard; on the bridge, groups from each town met to try to out-do the other in the volume of noise generated. Note the various kitchen implements which served as noisemakers; 21, overexposed photo; 22-26, The procession to the bridge; field coordinator Ray Brassieur can be seen with his tape recorder in #26; 27-34, Noisemakers on the bridge; the judges were on a truck parked in the middle of the bridge. The Canadians won; 35-36, A couple of VanrBuren residents enjoy the afternoon in their glider rocker.
    - Farrell-Michaud house, Van Buren, Maine; Variety of buildings and scenes, New Canada, Maine, and Fort Kent, Maine, July 13, 1991, AFC 1991/029: DW-B043-4029; David A. Whitman; 36 35 mm black-and-white film negatives
      These images document a variety of buildings and scenes; 2-6, The Farrell-Michaud House, an early twentieth century house in Van Buren, ME, which is listed on the National Register of Historic Places. The house is currently operated as a bed-and-breakfast; 8-9, Custom painted sign on a farm in New Canada; most farms in the study area have such signs; 10-14, Buildings with facades, New Canada, ME. This type of facade is often associated with commercial buildings, but many garages and other buildings on residential property have these facades; 15-16, A typical partially buried potato house in New Canada; the earth provides insulation for the produce; 17, Fieldworker David Whitman's truck is up to the axles in weeds; 18-19, Abandoned agricultural equipment, not an uncommon sight; 20, Mailbox set back (way back) from the road; this helps prevent damage from snow and snowplow; 21, Abandoned and collapsing potato house; 22-23, A man tins the roof on a farm building in New Canada. Tin was once a common roofing material but is used less today; 24, Scooter Helper, a repair business on State Highway 161 in Fort Kent, ME; many area residents operate small businesses from their homes; 25-26, Another garage with facade; 27-28, Rectangular clothesline, a common type in the area; 29, Shed with gambrel roof, locally called colm-casse; this roof style is used on a wide variety of buildings throughout the study area; 30-31, Trucks parked on a farm in Fort Kent; trucking is an important economic activity in the region, and many farmers are also shippers; 32-33, An independent trucker in Fort Kent; 34, A collection of farm buildings in Fort Kent; 35-36, Sign on a barn on the Daigle Bros, farm in Fort Kent; note the inclusion of shipping and trucking; 36a, Another garage with a facade in Fort Kent.
    - Grande Riviere Festival, Native American Day, Village Acadien, Van Buren, Maine, July 15, 1991, AFC 1991/029: DW-B044-4031; David A. Whitman; 36 35 mm black-and-white film negatives
      1-2, Sign on a barn south of Van Bur en on U.S. Highway 1; quite a few of the farmers in the study area combine trucking/shipping with farming; These images document an event called Native American Day, held at the Village Acadien in Van Buren, ME, as part of the annual Grande Riviere Festival; 3-4, A group of participants, most of whom are Mic-Mac from various reserves in New Brunswick, rehearse a song before the event. Event coordinator Guy Frigon (black hat) of Frenchville, ME, is one of the singer/drummers; 5-7, Participants rehearse in front of a tipi set up especially for this event; 10-11, This object hung over the door of the tipi; I collected no information about it; 12-14, Headdress hanging on a fence post; Frigon said that this is not a true Mic-Mac style, but more of a western or plains Indian style. They use this headdress for events like this because it represents what "white folks" expect to see; 15-16, Two of the participants talk with a spectator; 17-22, Guy Frigon and Kenny Cloud of the Red Bank Reserve in New Brunswick perform a ceremony in which the drum is blessed with tobacco; 23, A sweetgrass braid is lit; the smoldering braid will be used to purify both participants and spectators; 24-26, Participants are purified with smoke from the braid, fanned with feathers; 27, Birdhouse maker Albert Michaud watches the ceremony; 28-29, Participants sing and drum while Cloud circulates through the crowd with the sweetgrass braid; 30-32, Cloud purifies spectators; 33-34, Small wooden canoe carved by Kenny Cloud; 35-36, Frigon describes pipe ceremony.